<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Rust on A Rambling Mind </title>
    <link>https://fungos.github.io/tags/rust/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Danny Grein</author>
    <updated>2017-08-12 13:00:00 -0500 EST</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting Up a Rust Environment on Windows</title>
      <link>https://fungos.github.io/blog/2017/08/12/setting-up-a-rust-environment-on-windows/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2017 13:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>https://fungos.github.io/blog/2017/08/12/setting-up-a-rust-environment-on-windows/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;When I talk about Rust, one question that comes the most is about tooling and debugging. Online this can be seen a lot, mainly about debugging on Windows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to write a little guide mostly to practice my written English and bootstrap this blog, but also to document the current steps needed to set a good Windows Rust environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be warned that it may miss some details or be too superficial for some people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The setup described here is the one I&amp;rsquo;ve been using Rust on Windows (and approximately equivalent on GNU/Linux) for some time and I believe it to be the ideal setup for myself, at least for the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also believe that this setup is already better than current C or C++ (take it with a grain of salt anyway), first because of Cargo, but also due the recent improvements with &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rust-lang-nursery/rls&#34;&gt;Rust Language Server (RLS)&lt;/a&gt; and in part due to Rust use of LLVM and the compatibility with C ABI, it can piggyback on C/C++ tools like GDB, Valgrind, profilers and lots more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This makes setting up projects, developing and debugging a breeze if compared to C/C++, even if compared with Visual Studio and Visual Assist. Only Debugging is not as clean as debugging C code, its more like an equivalent of debugging a heavy STL C++ code base and some people may find this hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this may be helpfull in some way to these getting started with Rust on Windows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: My background is with C and C++, so I tend to compare things with these languages and probably use terminology from this background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;c-build-tools&#34;&gt;C++ Build Tools&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first and most important thing to a working Rust environment is to have one C++ toolchain available so Rust can build C or C++ (&amp;ldquo;-sys&amp;rdquo;) crates and link against Windows libraries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be achieved in two ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having a Visual Studio C++ installation, or;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Installing the smaller &lt;a href=&#34;http://landinghub.visualstudio.com/visual-cpp-build-tools&#34;&gt;Visual C++ Build Tools&lt;/a&gt; for a standalone toolchain;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;rustup&#34;&gt;Rustup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rustup is the responsible for managing Rust compilers, Cargo, documentation, and so on. This tool is the entry point for a complete Rust environment and as Cargo, is a central part of Rust tooling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: To avoid any confusion with older Rust installations, if you&amp;rsquo;d already tried Rust before without Rustup, I suggest to uninstall everything (Rust, Cargo and anything related).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Installing Rustup is straightforward, download it &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rustup.rs/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and then run it. A console window will launch as shown here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://fungos.github.io/images/1/rustup-console.png&#34; alt=&#34;rustup-init.exe&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then go with the default installation (option 1). As shown in the screenshot, it will install a stable Rust for MSVC ABI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or by command line:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-dos&#34;&gt;&amp;gt; rustup-init.exe -y
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;rust-toolchain&#34;&gt;Rust Toolchain&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Rustup installed, most of the toolchain management is done in the command line with the Rustup command. Getting used to it will surely help in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, lets update everything to be sure (required if it is not a fresh install):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-dos&#34;&gt;&amp;gt; rustup update
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, adding the nightly version of the compiler for trying experimental features and to be able to compile an useful tool (Clippy):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-dos&#34;&gt;&amp;gt; rustup install nightly
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;components&#34;&gt;Components&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three core components are recommended to be installed with Rustup so to have a full offline environment. Rust source and Rust documentation are not essential, but are nice to have if you may be offline while writing Rust. RLS on the other side, is essential and should be installed. You can read more about what RLS can do &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncameron.org/blog/what-the-rls-can-do/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, RLS will enable auto-completion and related code editing features to any IDE supporting the Microsoft Language Server protocol. It is in a way equivalent to C++ Intellisense or Visual Assist. Although it is still under heavy development, I think it is already more usable than both of C++ alternatives on Visual Studio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-dos&#34;&gt;&amp;gt; rustup component add rust-src
&amp;gt; rustup component add rust-docs
&amp;gt; rustup component add rls
&amp;gt; rustup update
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;rustfmt&#34;&gt;Rustfmt&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rustfmt will automatically format the code accordingly to the current code style standard. Opposed to languages as C or C++ where each code base has its own style, Rust (and for the matter, most recent languages) enforce a standard style on your code, you may think it is too intrusive, but it is better for everyone on the end. More information about styling can be found on rustfmt &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rust-lang-nursery/fmt-rfcs/blob/master/guide/guide.md&#34;&gt;RFC repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To install it, suffice to use Cargo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-dos&#34;&gt;&amp;gt; cargo install rustfmt
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be used by VSCode Rust Extension to automatically format Rust code being edited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: Rustfmt will be asked to be installed by Visual Studio Code if it isn&amp;rsquo;t already installed anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;clippy&#34;&gt;Clippy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clippy is another jewel of Rust, it is the second best friend (after Rust compiler) on helping learning Rust and improving the code. It is a linter that will catch issues and suggest improvements, it should be used regularly and will help learning some tricks and writing idiomatic code. The downside if we can say so is that it requires a nightly compiler to install/compile it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, to install, use Cargo (and be sure to have the nightly toolchain in use):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-dos&#34;&gt;&amp;gt; rustup default nightly
&amp;gt; cargo install clippy
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: Installing these tools with cargo means compiling them, and Rust compile times are not really the best. So, go take a coffee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: Clippy will be asked to be installed by Visual Studio Code if it isn&amp;rsquo;t already installed anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;visual-studio-code&#34;&gt;Visual Studio Code&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve tried some different IDEs, you can take a look &lt;a href=&#34;https://areweideyet.com/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for some alternatives IDEs, and their current support state. But from all these, I believe VSCode (at the moment) is the best and most complete mostly due to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Microsoft/language-server-protocol&#34;&gt;Language Server Protocol&lt;/a&gt;/RLS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: The second best is &lt;a href=&#34;https://intellij-rust.github.io/&#34;&gt;IntelliJ Rust&lt;/a&gt; and now it is &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.jetbrains.com/blog/2017/08/04/official-support-for-open-source-rust-plugin-for-intellij-idea-clion-and-other-jetbrains-ides/&#34;&gt;officially supported by JetBrains&lt;/a&gt;. The problem is that it is heavy. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t recommend it unless you&amp;rsquo;re already have it. Also, it does not support debugging, but this is being worked on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before configuring a Rust project in Visual Studio Code, some extensions are needed as these will help to edit code and debugging, and they&amp;rsquo;re pretty much all it is needed to have a working Rust IDE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;extensions&#34;&gt;Extensions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All VSCode extensions here may be installed via the Extensions Panel, or by using &lt;code&gt;CTRL+P&lt;/code&gt; and typing &lt;code&gt;ext install &amp;lt;name&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; or by command line:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-dos&#34;&gt;&amp;gt; code --install-extension &amp;lt;name&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;rust-rls&#34;&gt;Rust (rls)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/items?itemName=rust-lang.rust&#34;&gt;Rust (rls)&lt;/a&gt; is a new extension (the third Rust extension already) but is already very usable, also this is the official one by the Rust Tool Team and is being worked on actively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extension name: &lt;code&gt;rust-lang.rust&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-dos&#34;&gt;&amp;gt; code --install-extension rust-lang.rust
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;c-c&#34;&gt;C/C++&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This extension is needed to be able to debug native binaries using GDB, LLDB or Visual Studio Debugger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extension name: &lt;code&gt;ms-vscode.cpptools&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-dos&#34;&gt;&amp;gt; code --install-extension ms-vscode.cpptools
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will also download and install any required dependency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;native-debug&#34;&gt;Native Debug&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one is not really needed, but I recommend use this to automatically enable VSCode to set breakpoints on Rust code. Otherwise, it would require tuning user settings by setting &lt;code&gt;debug.allowBreakpointsEverywhere&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extension name: &lt;code&gt;webfreak.debug&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-dos&#34;&gt;&amp;gt; code --install-extension webfreak.debug
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;visualizers&#34;&gt;Visualizers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Rust MSVC toolchain comes some type visualizers for Visual Studio Debugger (Natvis), these can be used to ease the visualization of some very few Rust types within the Debugger. Sadly, there are still limitations of what can be specified in a Natvis file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The downside is that the installation of the visualization files are a bit manual at the moment, so this is the hardest part of all the Rust environment setup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The files in question are in &lt;code&gt;%HOMEPATH%\.rustup\toolchains\stable-x86_64-pc-windows-msvc\lib\rustlib\etc&lt;/code&gt; and must be copied to &lt;code&gt;%HOMEPATH%\.vscode\extensions\ms-vscode.cpptools-0.12.2\debugAdapters\vsdbg\bin\Visualizers&lt;/code&gt; (note the version on ms-vscode.cpptools path, this can be different for your case).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;debugging&#34;&gt;Debugging&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that everything is in place, the last thing is configuring a Rust project to be debugged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Create a debug configuration by going to the &lt;code&gt;(1) Debug Panel&lt;/code&gt;, then clicking on the &lt;code&gt;(2) Debug Configuration Dropdown&lt;/code&gt; and then select &lt;code&gt;(3) C++ (Windows)&lt;/code&gt; option as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://fungos.github.io/images/1/vscode-debug-cfg.png#center&#34; alt=&#34;debug&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://fungos.github.io/images/1/vscode-debug-msvc.png#center&#34; alt=&#34;debug&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will open a new file in the editor, called &lt;code&gt;launch.json&lt;/code&gt; where all launch settings are managed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial contents of the file aren&amp;rsquo;t good because VSCode does not know details about the loaded Rust project (and I don&amp;rsquo;t believe extensions can do anything here to help with it, at least for the current version), so a little tweak is required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current file should look as this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-json&#34;&gt;{
    &amp;quot;version&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;0.2.0&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;configurations&amp;quot;: [
        {
            &amp;quot;name&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;(Windows) Launch&amp;quot;,
            &amp;quot;type&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;cppvsdbg&amp;quot;,
            &amp;quot;request&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;launch&amp;quot;,
            &amp;quot;program&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;enter program name, for example ${workspaceRoot}/a.exe&amp;quot;,
            &amp;quot;args&amp;quot;: [],
            &amp;quot;stopAtEntry&amp;quot;: false,
            &amp;quot;cwd&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;${workspaceRoot}&amp;quot;,
            &amp;quot;environment&amp;quot;: [],
            &amp;quot;externalConsole&amp;quot;: true
        }
    ]
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some important things to note here are the &lt;code&gt;type&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;program&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;type&lt;/code&gt; should specify &lt;code&gt;cppvsdbg&lt;/code&gt; to use the MSVC Debugger and have Natvis support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;program&lt;/code&gt; here is the path to the executable generated by rustc/Cargo. When using Cargo, normally the debug executable will be found in a path as &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;project&amp;gt;/target/debug/&amp;lt;project&amp;gt;.exe&lt;/code&gt;. With this in mind, a good default should be to point the &lt;code&gt;program&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;${workspaceRoot}/target/debug/${workspaceRootFolderName}.exe&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My preferred &lt;code&gt;launch.json&lt;/code&gt; is this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-json&#34;&gt;{
    &amp;quot;version&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;0.2.0&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;configurations&amp;quot;: [
        {
            &amp;quot;name&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Debug&amp;quot;,
            &amp;quot;type&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;cppvsdbg&amp;quot;,
            &amp;quot;request&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;launch&amp;quot;,
            &amp;quot;program&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;${workspaceRoot}/target/debug/${workspaceRootFolderName}.exe&amp;quot;,
            &amp;quot;args&amp;quot;: [],
            &amp;quot;stopAtEntry&amp;quot;: false,
            &amp;quot;cwd&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;${workspaceRoot}&amp;quot;,
            &amp;quot;environment&amp;quot;: [],
            &amp;quot;externalConsole&amp;quot;: true
        },
        {
            &amp;quot;name&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Release&amp;quot;,
            &amp;quot;type&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;cppvsdbg&amp;quot;,
            &amp;quot;request&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;launch&amp;quot;,
            &amp;quot;program&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;${workspaceRoot}/target/release/${workspaceRootFolderName}.exe&amp;quot;,
            &amp;quot;args&amp;quot;: [],
            &amp;quot;stopAtEntry&amp;quot;: false,
            &amp;quot;cwd&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;${workspaceRoot}&amp;quot;,
            &amp;quot;environment&amp;quot;: [],
            &amp;quot;externalConsole&amp;quot;: true
        }
    ]
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this, a way to debug release binaries is already in hand if needed for some reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wishlist&#34;&gt;Wishlist&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The missing key step here would be to have a better integration from Rust Language Extension to manipulate/fix/generate &lt;code&gt;launch.json&lt;/code&gt; for Rust projects or even better, a &lt;code&gt;cargo ide-setup &amp;lt;ide&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; command or something similar, where &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;ide&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; could be &lt;code&gt;vscode&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This command would then be able to install the required vscode extensions if needed, and copy the natvis files to the right place, if in a windows environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;rust-env-setup-script&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;rust-env-setup&lt;/code&gt; Script&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a quick power shell script I hacked together in a gist for automatizing a working Rust environment with VSCode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: I&amp;rsquo;m not a PS guy, so do not take this for a solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script src=&#34;//gist.github.com/fungos/5c94a2b7ed4a5b7ea4572e54c0c96a34.js?file=rust-env-setup.ps1&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;feedback&#34;&gt;Feedback&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Help me improving this text by submitting fixes for wrong wording/phrasing or typos in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/fungos/fungos.github.io/issues&#34;&gt;this repo issue tracker&lt;/a&gt; or by commenting on twitter or elsewhere!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
